After well considering the matter while I was dressing at the Blue Boar in the morning, I resolved to tell my guardian that I doubted <PERSON>Orlick</PERSON>'s being the right sort of man to fill a post of trust at Miss Havisham's. "Why of course he is not the right sort of man, <PERSON>Pip</PERSON>," said my guardian, comfortably satisfied beforehand on the general head, "because the man who fills the post of trust never is the right sort of man." It seemed quite to put him into spirits to find that this particular post was not exceptionally held by the right sort of man, and he listened in a satisfied manner while I told him what knowledge I had of <PERSON>Orlick</PERSON>. "Very good, <PERSON>Pip</PERSON>," he observed, when I had concluded, "I'll go round presently, and pay our friend off." Rather alarmed by this summary action, I was for a little delay, and even hinted that our friend himself might be difficult to deal with. "Oh no he won't," said my guardian, making his pocket-handkerchief-point, with perfect confidence; "I should like to see him argue the question with me."

As we were going back together to <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> by the midday coach, and as I breakfasted under such terrors of <LOCATION>Pumblechook</LOCATION> that I could scarcely hold my cup, this gave me an opportunity of saying that I wanted a walk, and that I would go on along the <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> road while Mr. <PERSON>Jaggers</PERSON> was occupied, if he would let the coachman know that I would get into my place when overtaken. I was thus enabled to fly from the <ORGANIZATION>Blue</ORGANIZATION> <ORGANIZATION>Boar</ORGANIZATION> immediately after breakfast. By then making a loop of about a couple of miles into the open country at the back of <PERSON>Pumblechook</PERSON>'s premises, I got round into the High Street again, a little beyond that pitfall, and felt myself in comparative security.

It was interesting to be in the quiet old town once more, and it was not disagreeable to be here and there suddenly recognised and stared after. One or two of the tradespeople even darted out of their shops and went a little way down the street before me, that they might turn, as if they had forgotten something, and pass me face to face,--on which occasions I don't know whether they or I made the worse pretence; they of not doing it, or I of not seeing it. Still my position was a distinguished one, and I was not at all dissatisfied with it, until Fate threw me in the way of that unlimited miscreant, <PERSON>Trabb</PERSON>'s boy.

Casting my eyes along the street at a certain point of my progress, I beheld <PERSON>Trabb</PERSON>'s boy approaching, lashing himself with an empty blue bag. Deeming that a serene and unconscious contemplation of him would best beseem me, and would be most likely to quell his evil mind, I advanced with that expression of countenance, and was rather congratulating myself on my success, when suddenly the knees of <PERSON>Trabb</PERSON>'s boy smote together, his hair uprose, his cap fell off, he trembled violently in every limb, staggered out into the road, and crying to the populace, "Hold me! I'm so frightened!" feigned to be in a paroxysm of terror and contrition, occasioned by the dignity of my appearance. As I passed him, his teeth loudly chattered in his head, and with every mark of extreme humiliation, he prostrated himself in the dust.

This was a hard thing to bear, but this was nothing. I had not advanced another two hundred yards when, to my inexpressible terror, amazement, and indignation, I again beheld <PERSON>Trabb</PERSON>'s boy approaching. He was coming round a narrow corner. His blue bag was slung over his shoulder, honest industry beamed in his eyes, a determination to proceed to <PERSON>Trabb</PERSON>'s with cheerful briskness was indicated in his gait. With a shock he became aware of me, and was severely visited as before; but this time his motion was rotatory, and he staggered round and round me with knees more afflicted, and with uplifted hands as if beseeching for mercy. His sufferings were hailed with the greatest joy by a knot of spectators, and I felt utterly confounded.

I had not got as much further down the street as the post-office, when I again beheld <PERSON>Trabb</PERSON>'s boy shooting round by a back way. This time, he was entirely changed. He wore the blue bag in the manner of my great-coat, and was strutting along the pavement towards me on the opposite side of the street, attended by a company of delighted young friends to whom he from time to time exclaimed, with a wave of his hand, "Don't know yah!" Words cannot state the amount of aggravation and injury wreaked upon me by <PERSON>Trabb</PERSON>'s boy, when passing abreast of me, he pulled up his shirt-collar, twined his side-hair, stuck an arm akimbo, and smirked extravagantly by, wriggling his elbows and body, and drawling to his attendants, "Don't know yah, don't know yah, 'pon my soul don't know yah!" The disgrace attendant on his immediately afterwards taking to crowing and pursuing me across the bridge with crows, as from an exceedingly dejected fowl who had known me when I was a blacksmith, culminated the disgrace with which I left the town, and was, so to speak, ejected by it into the open country.
0245m

But unless I had taken the life of <PERSON>Trabb</PERSON>'s boy on that occasion, I really do not even now see what I could have done save endure. To have struggled with him in the street, or to have exacted any lower recompense from him than his heart's best blood, would have been futile and degrading. Moreover, he was a boy whom no man could hurt; an invulnerable and dodging serpent who, when chased into a corner, flew out again between his captor's legs, scornfully yelping. I wrote, however, to Mr. <PERSON>Trabb</PERSON> by next day's post, to say that Mr. <PERSON>Pip</PERSON> must decline to deal further with one who could so far forget what he owed to the best interests of society, as to employ a boy who excited Loathing in every respectable mind.

The coach, with Mr. <PERSON>Jaggers</PERSON> inside, came up in due time, and I took my box-seat again, and arrived in <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> safe,--but not sound, for my heart was gone. As soon as I arrived, I sent a penitential codfish and barrel of oysters to <PERSON>Joe</PERSON> (as reparation for not having gone myself), and then went on to <PERSON>Barnard</PERSON>'s Inn.
