Mr. <PERSON>Wopsle</PERSON>'s great-aunt kept an evening school in the village; that is to say, she was a ridiculous old woman of limited means and unlimited infirmity, who used to go to sleep from six to seven every evening, in the society of youth who paid two pence per week each, for the improving opportunity of seeing her do it. She rented a small cottage, and Mr. <PERSON>Wopsle</PERSON> had the room upstairs, where we students used to overhear him reading aloud in a most dignified and terrific manner, and occasionally bumping on the ceiling. There was a fiction that Mr. <PERSON>Wopsle</PERSON> "examined" the scholars once a quarter. What he did on those occasions was to turn up his cuffs, stick up his hair, and give us <PERSON>Mark</PERSON> <PERSON>Antony</PERSON>'s oration over the body of <PERSON>Caesar</PERSON>. This was always followed by <PERSON>Collins</PERSON>'s Ode on the Passions, wherein I particularly venerated Mr. <PERSON>Wopsle</PERSON> as Revenge throwing his blood-stained sword in thunder down, and taking the War-denouncing trumpet with a withering look. It was not with me then, as it was in later life, when I fell into the society of the Passions, and compared them with <PERSON>Collins</PERSON> and <PERSON>Wopsle</PERSON>, rather to the disadvantage of both gentlemen.

Mr. <PERSON>Wopsle</PERSON>'s great-aunt, besides keeping this Educational Institution, kept in the same room--a little general shop. She had no idea what stock she had, or what the price of anything in it was; but there was a little greasy memorandum-book kept in a drawer, which served as a Catalogue of Prices, and by this oracle <PERSON>Biddy</PERSON> arranged all the shop transactions. <PERSON>Biddy</PERSON> was Mr. <PERSON>Wopsle</PERSON>'s great-aunt's granddaughter; I confess myself quite unequal to the working out of the problem, what relation she was to Mr. <PERSON>Wopsle</PERSON>. She was an orphan like myself; like me, too, had been brought up by hand. She was most noticeable, I thought, in respect of her extremities; for, her hair always wanted brushing, her hands always wanted washing, and her shoes always wanted mending and pulling up at heel. This description must be received with a week-day limitation. On Sundays, she went to church elaborated.

Much of my unassisted self, and more by the help of <PERSON>Biddy</PERSON> than of Mr. <PERSON>Wopsle</PERSON>'s great-aunt, I struggled through the alphabet as if it had been a bramble-bush; getting considerably worried and scratched by every letter. After that I fell among those thieves, the nine figures, who seemed every evening to do something new to disguise themselves and baffle recognition. But, at last I began, in a purblind groping way, to read, write, and cipher, on the very smallest scale.

One night I was sitting in the chimney corner with my slate, expending great efforts on the production of a letter to <PERSON>Joe</PERSON>. I think it must have been a full year after our hunt upon the marshes, for it was a long time after, and it was winter and a hard frost. With an alphabet on the hearth at my feet for reference, I contrived in an hour or two to print and smear this epistle:--

"MI DEER JO i OPE U R KRWITE WELL i OPE i SHAL
SON B HABELL 4 2 TEEDGE U JO AN THEN WE SHORL B
SO GLODD AN WEN i M PRENGTD 2 U JO WOT LARX AN
BLEVE ME INF XN PIP."

There was no indispensable necessity for my communicating with <PERSON>Joe</PERSON> by letter, inasmuch as he sat beside me and we were alone. But I delivered this written communication (slate and all) with my own hand, and <PERSON>Joe</PERSON> received it as a miracle of erudition.

"I say, <PERSON>Pip</PERSON>, old chap!" cried <PERSON>Joe</PERSON>, opening his blue eyes wide, "what a scholar you are! An't you?"

"I should like to be," said I, glancing at the slate as he held it; with a misgiving that the writing was rather hilly.

"Why, here's a J," said <PERSON>Joe</PERSON>, "and a O equal to anythink! Here's a J and a O, Pip, and a J-O, <PERSON>Joe</PERSON>."
0072m

I had never heard <PERSON>Joe</PERSON> read aloud to any greater extent than this monosyllable, and I had observed at church last Sunday, when I accidentally held our <LOCATION>Prayer-Book</LOCATION> upside down, that it seemed to suit his convenience quite as well as if it had been all right. Wishing to embrace the present occasion of finding out whether in teaching <PERSON>Joe</PERSON>, I should have to begin quite at the beginning, I said, "Ah! But read the rest, <PERSON>Jo</PERSON>."

"The rest, eh, Pip?" said <PERSON>Joe</PERSON>, looking at it with a slow, searching eye, "One, two, three. Why, here's three Js, and three Os, and three J-O, Joes in it, Pip!"

I leaned over <PERSON>Joe</PERSON>, and, with the aid of my forefinger read him the whole letter.

"Astonishing!" said <PERSON>Joe</PERSON>, when I had finished. "You ARE a scholar."

"How do you spell Gargery, <PERSON>Joe</PERSON>?" I asked him, with a modest patronage.

"I don't spell it at all," said <PERSON>Joe</PERSON>.

"But supposing you did?"

"It can't be supposed," said <PERSON>Joe</PERSON>. "Tho' I'm uncommon fond of reading, too."

"Are you, <PERSON>Joe</PERSON>?"

"On-common. Give me," said <PERSON>Joe</PERSON>, "a good book, or a good newspaper, and sit me down afore a good fire, and I ask no better. Lord!" he continued, after rubbing his knees a little, "when you do come to a J and a O, and says you, 'Here, at last, is a J-O, <PERSON>Joe</PERSON>,' how interesting reading is!"
