Mr. <PERSON>Wopsle</PERSON>, the clerk at church, was to dine with us; and Mr. <PERSON>Hubble</PERSON> the wheelwright and Mrs. <PERSON>Hubble</PERSON>; and <PERSON>Uncle</PERSON> <PERSON>Pumblechook</PERSON> (<PERSON>Joe</PERSON>'s uncle, but Mrs. <PERSON>Joe</PERSON> appropriated him), who was a well-to-do cornchandler in the nearest town, and drove his own chaise-cart. The dinner hour was half-past one. When <PERSON>Joe</PERSON> and I got home, we found the table laid, and Mrs. <PERSON>Joe</PERSON> dressed, and the dinner dressing, and the front door unlocked (it never was at any other time) for the company to enter by, and everything most splendid. And still, not a word of the robbery.

The time came, without bringing with it any relief to my feelings, and the company came. Mr. <PERSON>Wopsle</PERSON>, united to a Roman nose and a large shining bald forehead, had a deep voice which he was uncommonly proud of; indeed it was understood among his acquaintance that if you could only give him his head, he would read the clergyman into fits; he himself confessed that if the Church was "thrown open," meaning to competition, he would not despair of making his mark in it. The Church not being "thrown open," he was, as I have said, our clerk. But he punished the Amens tremendously; and when he gave out the psalm,--always giving the whole verse,--he looked all round the congregation first, as much as to say, "You have heard my friend overhead; oblige me with your opinion of this style!"

I opened the door to the company,--making believe that it was a habit of ours to open that door,--and I opened it first to Mr. <PERSON>Wopsle</PERSON>, next to Mr. and Mrs. <PERSON>Hubble</PERSON>, and last of all to <PERSON>Uncle</PERSON> <PERSON>Pumblechook</PERSON>. N.B. I was not allowed to call him uncle, under the severest penalties.

"Mrs. <PERSON>Joe</PERSON>," said <PERSON>Uncle</PERSON> <PERSON>Pumblechook</PERSON>, a large hard-breathing middle-aged slow man, with a mouth like a fish, dull staring eyes, and sandy hair standing upright on his head, so that he looked as if he had just been all but choked, and had that moment come to, "I have brought you as the compliments of the season--I have brought you, Mum, a bottle of sherry wine--and I have brought you, Mum, a bottle of port wine."

Every Christmas Day he presented himself, as a profound novelty, with exactly the same words, and carrying the two bottles like dumb-bells. Every Christmas Day, Mrs. <PERSON>Joe</PERSON> replied, as she now replied, "O, Un--cle Pum-ble--chook! This is kind!" Every Christmas Day, he retorted, as he now retorted, "It's no more than your merits. And now are you all bobbish, and how's Sixpennorth of halfpence?" meaning me.

We dined on these occasions in the kitchen, and adjourned, for the nuts and oranges and apples to the parlour; which was a change very like <PERSON>Joe</PERSON>'s change from his working-clothes to his Sunday dress. My sister was uncommonly lively on the present occasion, and indeed was generally more gracious in the society of Mrs. <PERSON>Hubble</PERSON> than in other company. I remember Mrs. <PERSON>Hubble</PERSON> as a little curly sharp-edged person in sky-blue, who held a conventionally juvenile position, because she had married Mr. <PERSON>Hubble</PERSON>,--I don't know at what remote period,--when she was much younger than he. I remember <PERSON>Mr</PERSON> <PERSON>Hubble</PERSON> as a tough, high-shouldered, stooping old man, of a sawdusty fragrance, with his legs extraordinarily wide apart: so that in my short days I always saw some miles of open country between them when I met him coming up the lane.

Among this good company I should have felt myself, even if I hadn't robbed the pantry, in a false position. Not because I was squeezed in at an acute angle of the tablecloth, with the table in my chest, and the Pumblechookian elbow in my eye, nor because I was not allowed to speak (I didn't want to speak), nor because I was regaled with the scaly tips of the drumsticks of the fowls, and with those obscure corners of pork of which the pig, when living, had had the least reason to be vain. No; I should not have minded that, if they would only have left me alone. But they wouldn't leave me alone. They seemed to think the opportunity lost, if they failed to point the conversation at me, every now and then, and stick the point into me. I might have been an unfortunate little bull in a Spanish arena, I got so smartingly touched up by these moral goads.

It began the moment we sat down to dinner. Mr. <PERSON>Wopsle</PERSON> said grace with theatrical declamation,--as it now appears to me, something like a religious cross of the Ghost in <LOCATION>Hamlet</LOCATION> with <PERSON>Richard</PERSON> the Third,--and ended with the very proper aspiration that we might be truly grateful. Upon which my sister fixed me with her eye, and said, in a low reproachful voice, "Do you hear that? Be grateful."

"Especially," said Mr. <PERSON>Pumblechook</PERSON>, "be grateful, boy, to them which brought you up by hand."

Mrs. <PERSON>Hubble</PERSON> shook her head, and contemplating me with a mournful presentiment that I should come to no good, asked, "Why is it that the young are never grateful?" This moral mystery seemed too much for the company until Mr. <PERSON>Hubble</PERSON> tersely solved it by saying, "Naterally wicious." Everybody then murmured "True!" and looked at me in a particularly unpleasant and personal manner.
