<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Vanity Fair: A Novel without a Hero: ELTeC edition</title>
           <author ref="https://viaf.org/viaf/95208604/">Thackeray, William Makepeace (1811-1863)</author>
        </titleStmt>
        <extent>
           <measure unit="words">298740</measure>
        </extent>
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher ref="https://distant-reading.net">COST Action "Distant Reading for European Literary History" (CA16204)</publisher>
           <distributor ref="https://zenodo.org/communities/eltec/">Zenodo.org</distributor><date when="2020-11-14"/>
           <availability><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/></availability>
           <ref type="doi" target="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.3462435">ELTeC</ref>
           <ref type="doi" target="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4271467">ELTeC release 1.0.0</ref>
           <ref type="doi" target="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.3533868">ELTeC-eng</ref>
           <ref type="doi" target="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4271630">ELTeC-eng release 1.0.0</ref>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc><bibl type="digitalSource"><author>Thackeray, William Makepeace</author>
           <title>Vanity Fair, A Novel without a Hero. Vols. V &amp; VI</title>
           <title level="s">Harvard Classics Shelf of Fiction.</title>
           <publisher>New York: P.F. Collier &amp; Son, 1917</publisher>
           <publisher>Bartleby.com, 2000.</publisher>
           <ref target="http://www.bartleby.com/305/">Bartleby</ref></bibl>
           <bibl type="firstEdition" n="B7155">
              <author>W. M. Thackeray</author>
              <title>Vanity Fair: A Novel without a Hero</title>
              <publisher>London: Bradbury and Evans</publisher>
              <date>1848</date>
              <ref target="http://dbooks.bodleian.ox.ac.uk/books/PDFs/590972833.pdf"/>
           </bibl></sourceDesc>
     </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="chapter">
            <head>I. Chiswick Mall</head>
            <p>WHILE the present century was in its teens, and on one sunshiny morning in
               June, there drove up to the great iron gate of Miss Pinkerton’s academy for
               young ladies, on Chiswick Mall, a large family coach, with two fat horses in
               blazing harness, driven by a fat coachman in a three-cornered hat and wig,
               at the rate of four miles an hour. A black servant, who reposed on the box
               beside the fat coachman, uncurled his bandy legs as soon as the equipage
               drew up opposite Miss Pinkerton’s shining brass plate, and as he pulled the
               bell, at least a score of young heads were seen peering out of the narrow
               windows of the stately old brick house. Nay, the acute observer might have
               recognized the little red nose of good-natured Miss Jemima Pinkerton
               herself, rising over some geranium-pots in the window of that lady’s own
               drawing-room.</p>
            <p>  “It is Mrs. Sedley’s coach, sister,” said Miss Jemima “Sambo, the black
               servant, has just rung the bell; and the coachman has a new red
               waistcoat.”</p>
            <p>  “Have you completed all the necessary preparations incident to Miss
               Sedley’s departure, Miss Jemima?” asked Miss Pinkerton herself, that
               majestic lady; the Semiramis of Hammersmith, the friend of Doctor Johnson,
               the correspondent of Mrs. Chapone herself.</p>
            <p>  “The girls were up at four this morning, packing her trunks, sister,”
               replied Miss Jemima; “we have made her a bow-pot.”</p>
            <p>  “Say a bouquet, sister Jemima, ’tis more genteel.”</p>
            <p>  “Well, a booky as big almost as a hay-stack; I have put up two bottles of
               the gillyflower-water for Mrs. Sedley, and the receipt for making it, in
               Amelia’s box.”</p>
            <p>  “And I trust, Miss Jemima, you have made a copy of Miss Sedley’s account.
               This is it, is it? Very good—ninety-three pounds, four shillings. Be kind
               enough to address it to John Sedley, Esquire, and to seal this billet which
               I have written to his lady.”</p>
            <p>  In Miss Jemima’s eyes an autograph letter of her sister, Miss Pinkerton,
               was an object of as deep veneration as would have been a letter from a
               sovereign. Only when her pupils quitted the establishment, or when they were
               about to be married, and once, when poor Miss Birch died of the scarlet
               fever, was Miss Pinkerton known to write personally to the parents of her
               pupils; and it was Jemima’s opinion that if anything <hi>could</hi> console
               Mrs. Birch for her daughter’s loss, it would be that pious and eloquent
               composition in which Miss Pinkerton announced the event.</p>
            <p>  In the present instance Miss Pinkerton’s “billet” was to the following
               effect:— <quote><p>  “MADAM—After her six years’ residence at the Mall, I
                  have the honour and happiness of presenting Miss Amelia Sedley to
                  her parents, as a young lady not unworthy to occupy a fitting
                  position in their polished and refined circle. Those virtues which
                  characterise the young English gentlewoman, those accomplishments
                  which become her birth and station, will not be found wanting in the
                  amiable Miss Sedley, whose <hi>industry</hi> and <hi>obedience</hi>
                  have endeared her to her instructors, and whose delightful sweetness
                  of temper has charmed her <hi>aged</hi> and her <hi>youthful</hi>
                  companions.</p><p>  “In music, in dancing, in orthography, in every
                     variety of embroidery and needle-work, she will be found to have
                     realised her friends’ <hi>fondest wishes.</hi> In geography there is
                     still much to be desired; and a careful and undeviating use of the
                     backboard, for four hours daily during the next three years, is
                     recommended as necessary to the acquirement of that dignified
                     <hi>deportment and carriage,</hi> so requisite for every young
                     lady of <hi>fashion.</hi></p><p>  “In the principles of religion and
                        morality, Miss Sedley will be found worthy of an establishment which
                        has been honoured by the presence of <hi>The Great
                           Lexicographer,</hi> and the patronage of the admirable Mrs.
                        Chapone. In leaving the Mall, Miss Amelia carries with her the
                        hearts of her companions, and the affectionate regards of her
                        mistress, who has the honour to subscribe
                        herself,</p><p>  “P.S.—Miss Sharp accompanies Miss Sedley. It is
                           particularly requested that Miss Sharp’s stay in Russell Square may
                           not exceed ten days. The family of distinction with whom she is
                           engaged, desire to avail themselves of her services as soon as
                           possible.”</p></quote></p>
            <p>  This letter completed, Miss Pinkerton proceeded to write her own name, and
               Miss Sedley’s, in the fly-leaf of a Johnson’s Dictionary—the interesting
               work which she invariably presented to her scholars, on their departure from
               the Mall. On the cover was inserted a copy of “Lines addressed to a young
               lady on quitting Miss Pinkerton’s school, at the Mall; by the late revered
               Doctor Samuel Johnson.” In fact, the Lexicographer’s name was always on the
               lips of this majestic woman, and a visit he had paid to her was the cause of
               her reputation and her fortune.</p>
            <p>  Being commanded by her elder sister to get “the Dictionary” from the
               cupboard, Miss Jemima had extracted two copies of the book from the
               receptacle in question. When Miss Pinkerton had finished the inscription in
               the first, Jemima, with rather a dubious and timid air, handed her the
               second.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
