<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
         <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
               <title>The Channings : ELTeC edition</title>
               <author ref="viaf:14898332">Wood, Ellen (1814-1887)</author>
               <respStmt>
                  <resp>Text file produced by </resp>
                  <name>Jonathan Ingram</name>
                  <name>Charlie Kirschner</name>
                  <name>Distributed Proofreading Team</name>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <resp>HTML file produced by</resp>
                  <name>David Widger </name>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <resp>ELTeC conversion</resp>
                  <name>Lou Burnard</name>
               </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <extent>
               <measure unit="words">199639</measure>
            </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
               <publisher ref="https://distant-reading.net">COST Action "Distant Reading for
                  European Literary History" (CA16204)</publisher>
               <distributor ref="https://zenodo.org/communities/eltec/">Zenodo.org</distributor>
               <date when="2019-11-09"/>
               <availability>
                  <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
               </availability>
               <ref type="doi" target="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.3462435"/>
               
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
               <bibl type="digitalSource"><title>The Project Gutenberg EBook of The
                  Channings</title>
                  <author>Mrs. Henry Wood</author>
                  <ref target="http://www.gutenberg.org/9/1/9/9192/">PG source</ref>
                  <idno type="PG">9192</idno>
               </bibl>
               <bibl type="printSource"><title>The Channings</title><author>Mrs Henry
                  Wood</author>
                  <publisher>London: Bentley</publisher><date>1862</date></bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
         </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="chapter">
            <head>CHAPTER I. — THE INKED SURPLICE.</head>
            <p>The sweet bells of Helstonleigh Cathedral were ringing out in the summer’s
               afternoon. Groups of people lined the streets, in greater number than the
               ordinary business of the day would have brought forth; some pacing with
               idle steps, some halting to talk with one another, some looking in silence
               towards a certain point, as far as the eye could reach; all waiting in
               expectation.</p>
            <p>It was the first day of Helstonleigh Assizes; that is, the day on which the
               courts of law began their sittings. Generally speaking, the commission was
               opened at Helstonleigh on a Saturday; but for some convenience in the
               arrangements of the circuit, it was fixed this time for Wednesday; and when
               those cathedral bells burst forth, they gave signal that the judges had
               arrived and were entering the sheriff’s carriage, which had gone out to
               meet them.</p>
            <p>A fine sight, carrying in it much of majesty, was the procession, as it
               passed through the streets with its slow and stately steps; and although
               Helstonleigh saw it twice a year, it looked at it with gratified eyes
               still, and made the day into a sort of holiday. The trumpeters rode first,
               blowing the proud note of advance, and the long line of well-mounted
               javelin men came next, two abreast; their attire that of the livery of the
               high sheriff’s family, and their javelins held in rest. Sundry officials
               followed, and the governor of the county gaol sat in an open carriage, his
               long white wand raised in the air. Then appeared the handsome, closed
               equipage of the sheriff, its four horses, caparisoned with silver, pawing
               the ground, for they chafed at the slow pace to which they were restrained.
               In it, in their scarlet robes and flowing wigs, carrying awe to many a
               young spectator, sat the judges. The high sheriff sat opposite to them, his
               chaplain by his side, in his gown and bands. A crowd of gentlemen, friends
               of the sheriff, followed on horseback; and a mob of ragamuffins brought up
               the rear.</p>
            <p>To the assize courts the procession took its way, and there the short
               business of opening the commission was gone through, when the judges
               re-entered the carriage to proceed to the cathedral, having been joined by
               the mayor and corporation. The sweet bells of Helstonleigh were still
               ringing out, not to welcome the judges to the city now, but as an
               invitation to them to come and worship God. Within the grand entrance of
               the cathedral, waiting to receive the judges, stood the Dean of
               Helstonleigh, two or three of the chapter, two of the minor canons, and the
               king’s scholars and choristers, all in their white robes. The bells ceased;
               the fine organ pealed out—and there are few finer organs in England than
               that of Helstonleigh—the vergers with their silver maces, and the decrepit
               old bedesmen in their black gowns, led the way to the choir, the long
               scarlet trains of the judges held up behind: and places were found for
               all.</p>
            <p>The Rev. John Pye began the service; it was his week for chanting. He was one
               of the senior minor canons, and head-master of the college school. At the
               desk opposite to him sat the Rev. William Yorke, a young man who had only
               just gained his minor canonry.</p>
            <p>The service went on smoothly until the commencement of the anthem. In one
               sense it went on smoothly to the end, for no person present, not even the
               judges themselves, could see that anything was wrong. Mr. Pye was what was
               called “chanter” to the cathedral, which meant that it was he who had the
               privilege of selecting the music for the chants and other portions of the
               service, when the dean did not do so himself. The anthem he had put up for
               this occasion was a very good one, taken from the Psalms of David. It
               commenced with a treble solo; it was, moreover, an especial favourite of
               Mr. Pye’s; and he complacently disposed himself to listen.</p>
            <p>But no sooner was the symphony over, no sooner had the first notes of the
               chorister sounded on Mr. Pye’s ear, than his face slightly flushed, and he
               lifted his head with a sharp, quick gesture. <hi rend="italic">That</hi>
               was not the voice which ought to have sung this fine anthem; that was a
               cracked, <hi rend="italic">passée</hi> voice, belonging to the senior
               chorister, a young gentleman of seventeen, who was going out of the choir
               at Michaelmas. He had done good service for the choir in his day, but his
               voice was breaking now; and the last time he had attempted a solo, the
               bishop (who interfered most rarely with the executive of the cathedral;
               and, indeed, it was not his province to do so) had spoken himself to Mr.
               Pye on the conclusion of the service, and said the boy ought not to be
               allowed to sing alone again.</p>
            <p>Mr. Pye bent his head forward to catch a glimpse of the choristers, five of
               whom sat on his side of the choir, the <hi rend="italic">decani</hi>; five
               on the opposite, or <hi rend="italic">cantori</hi> side. So far as he could
               see, the boy, Stephen Bywater, who ought to have taken the anthem, was not
               in his place. There appeared to be only four of them; but the senior boy
               with his clean, starched surplice, partially hid those below him. Mr. Pye
               wondered where his eyes could have been, not to have noticed the boy’s
               absence when they had all been gathered round the entrance, waiting for the
               judges.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
