<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Vanity Fair: A Novel without a Hero: ELTeC edition</title>
           <author ref="https://viaf.org/viaf/95208604/">Thackeray, William Makepeace (1811-1863)</author>
        </titleStmt>
        <extent>
           <measure unit="words">298740</measure>
        </extent>
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher ref="https://distant-reading.net">COST Action "Distant Reading for European Literary History" (CA16204)</publisher>
           <distributor ref="https://zenodo.org/communities/eltec/">Zenodo.org</distributor><date when="2020-11-14"/>
           <availability><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/></availability>
           <ref type="doi" target="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.3462435">ELTeC</ref>
           <ref type="doi" target="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4271467">ELTeC release 1.0.0</ref>
           <ref type="doi" target="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.3533868">ELTeC-eng</ref>
           <ref type="doi" target="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4271630">ELTeC-eng release 1.0.0</ref>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc><bibl type="digitalSource"><author>Thackeray, William Makepeace</author>
           <title>Vanity Fair, A Novel without a Hero. Vols. V &amp; VI</title>
           <title level="s">Harvard Classics Shelf of Fiction.</title>
           <publisher>New York: P.F. Collier &amp; Son, 1917</publisher>
           <publisher>Bartleby.com, 2000.</publisher>
           <ref target="http://www.bartleby.com/305/">Bartleby</ref></bibl>
           <bibl type="firstEdition" n="B7155">
              <author>W. M. Thackeray</author>
              <title>Vanity Fair: A Novel without a Hero</title>
              <publisher>London: Bradbury and Evans</publisher>
              <date>1848</date>
              <ref target="http://dbooks.bodleian.ox.ac.uk/books/PDFs/590972833.pdf"/>
           </bibl></sourceDesc>
     </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <p>  Rebecca had never seen a Baronet, as far as she knew, and as soon as she
            had taken leave of Amelia, and counted the guineas which good-natured Mr.
            Sedley had put into a purse for her, and as soon as she had done wiping her
            eyes with her handkerchief (which operation she concluded the very moment
            the carriage had turned the corner of the street), she began to depict in
            her own mind what a baronet must be. “I wonder, does he wear a star?”
            thought she, “or is it only lords that wear stars? But he will be very
            handsomely dressed in a court suit, with ruffles, and his hair a little
            powdered, like Mr. Wroughton at Covent Garden. I suppose he will be awfully
            proud, and that I shall be treated most contemptuously. Still I must bear my
            hard lot as well as I can—at least, I shall be amongst <hi>gentlefolks,</hi>
            and not with vulgar city people:” and she fell to thinking of her Russell
            Square friends with that very same philosophical bitterness with which, in a
            certain apologue, the fox is represented as speaking of the grapes.</p>
         <p>  Having passed through Gaunt Square into Great Gaunt Street, the carriage at
            length stopped at a tall gloomy house between two other tall gloomy houses,
            each with a hatchment over the middle drawing-room window; as is the custom
            of houses in Great Gaunt Street, in which gloomy locality death seems to
            reign perpetual. The shutters of the first-floor windows of Sir Pitt’s
            mansion were closed—those of the dining-room were partially open, and the
            blinds neatly covered up in old newspapers.</p>
         <p>  John, the groom, who had driven the carriage alone, did not care to descend
            to ring the bell; and so prayed a passing milk-boy to perform that office
            for him. When the bell was rung, a head appeared between the interstices of
            the dining-room shutters, and the door was opened by a man in drab breeches
            and gaiters, with a dirty old coat, a foul old neckcloth lashed round his
            bristly neck, a shining bald head, a leering red face, a pair of twinkling
            grey eyes, and a mouth perpetually on the grin.</p>
         <p>  “This Sir Pitt Crawley’s?” says John, from the box.</p>
         <p>  “Ees,” says the man at the door, with a nod.</p>
         <p>  “Hand down these ’ere trunks, then,” said John.</p>
         <p>  “Hand ’n down yourself,” said the porter.</p>
         <p>  “Don’t you see I can’t leave my hosses? Come, bear a hand, my fine feller,
            and Miss will give you some beer,” said John, with a horse-laugh, for he was
            no longer respectful to Miss Sharp, as her connexion with the family was
            broken off, and as she had given nothing to the servants on coming away.</p>
         <p>  The bald-headed man, taking his hands out of his breeches pockets, advanced
            on this summons, and throwing Miss Sharp’s trunk over his shoulder, carried
            it into the house.</p>
         <p>  “Take this basket and shawl, if you please, and open the door,” said Miss
            Sharp, and descended from the carriage in much indignation. “I shall write
            to Mr. Sedley and inform him of your conduct,” said she to the groom.</p>
         <p>  “Don’t,” replied that functionary. “I hope you’ve forgot nothink? Miss
            ’Melia’s gownds—have you got them—as the lady’s maid was to have ’ad? I hope
            they’ll fit you. Shut the door, Jim, you’ll get no good out of
            <hi>’er,”</hi> continued John, pointing with his thumb towards Miss
            Sharp; “a bad lot, I tell you, a bad lot,” and so saying, Mr. Sedley’s groom
            drove away. The truth is, he was attached to the lady’s maid in question,
            and indignant that she should have been robbed of her perquisites.</p>
         <p>  On entering the dining-room, by the orders of the individual in gaiters,
            Rebecca found that apartment not more cheerful than such rooms usually are,
            when genteel families are out of town. The faithful chambers seem, as it
            were, to mourn the absence of their masters. The turkey carpet has rolled
            itself up, and retired sulkily under the sideboard: the pictures have hidden
            their faces behind old sheets of brown paper: the ceiling lamp is muffled up
            in a dismal sack of brown holland: the window-curtains have disappeared
            under all sorts of shabby envelopes: the marble bust of Sir Walpole Crawley
            is looking from its black corner at the bare boards and the oiled
            fire-irons, and the empty card-racks over the mantel-piece: the cellaret has
            lurked away behind the carpet: the chairs are turned up heads and tails
            along the walls: and in the dark corner opposite the statue, is an
            old-fashioned crabbed knife-box locked and sitting on a dumb waiter.</p>
         <p>  Two kitchen chairs, and a round table, and an attenuated old poker and
            tongs were, however, gathered round the fire-place, as was a saucepan over a
            feeble sputtering fire. There was a bit of cheese and bread, and a tin
            candlestick on the table, and a little black porter in a pint-pot.</p>
         <p>  “Had your dinner, I suppose? It is not too warm for you? Like a drop of
            beer?”</p>
         <p>  “Where is Sir Pitt Crawley?” said Miss Sharp majestically.</p>
         <p>  “He, he! I’m Sir Pitt Crawley. Reklect you owe me a pint for bringing down
            your luggage. He, he! Ask Tinker if I aynt. Mrs. Tinker, Miss Sharp; Miss
            Governess, Mrs. Charwoman. Ho, ho!”</p>
         <p>  The lady addressed as Mrs. Tinker, at this moment made her appearance with
            a pipe and a paper of tobacco, for which she had been despatched a minute
            before Miss Sharp’s arrival; and she handed the articles over to Sir Pitt,
            who had taken his seat by the fire.</p>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
