<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Vanity Fair: A Novel without a Hero: ELTeC edition</title>
           <author ref="https://viaf.org/viaf/95208604/">Thackeray, William Makepeace (1811-1863)</author>
        </titleStmt>
        <extent>
           <measure unit="words">298740</measure>
        </extent>
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher ref="https://distant-reading.net">COST Action "Distant Reading for European Literary History" (CA16204)</publisher>
           <distributor ref="https://zenodo.org/communities/eltec/">Zenodo.org</distributor><date when="2020-11-14"/>
           <availability><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/></availability>
           <ref type="doi" target="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.3462435">ELTeC</ref>
           <ref type="doi" target="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4271467">ELTeC release 1.0.0</ref>
           <ref type="doi" target="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.3533868">ELTeC-eng</ref>
           <ref type="doi" target="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4271630">ELTeC-eng release 1.0.0</ref>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc><bibl type="digitalSource"><author>Thackeray, William Makepeace</author>
           <title>Vanity Fair, A Novel without a Hero. Vols. V &amp; VI</title>
           <title level="s">Harvard Classics Shelf of Fiction.</title>
           <publisher>New York: P.F. Collier &amp; Son, 1917</publisher>
           <publisher>Bartleby.com, 2000.</publisher>
           <ref target="http://www.bartleby.com/305/">Bartleby</ref></bibl>
           <bibl type="firstEdition" n="B7155">
              <author>W. M. Thackeray</author>
              <title>Vanity Fair: A Novel without a Hero</title>
              <publisher>London: Bradbury and Evans</publisher>
              <date>1848</date>
              <ref target="http://dbooks.bodleian.ox.ac.uk/books/PDFs/590972833.pdf"/>
           </bibl></sourceDesc>
     </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="chapter">
            <head>VIII. Private and Confidential</head>
            <p>  Everything considered, I think it is quite as well for our dear Amelia
               Sedley, in Russell Square, that Miss Sharp and she are parted. Rebecca is a
               droll funny creature, to be sure; and those descriptions of the poor lady
               weeping for the loss of her beauty, and the gentleman “with hay-coloured
               whiskers and straw-coloured hair,” are very smart, doubtless, and show a
               great knowledge of the world. That she might, when on her knees, have been
               thinking of something better than Miss Horrock’s ribbons, has possibly
               struck both of us. But my kind reader will please to remember that this
               history has “Vanity Fair” for a title, and that Vanity Fair is a very vain,
               wicked, foolish place, full of all sorts of humbugs and falseness and
               pretensions. And while the moralist, who is holding forth on the cover (an
               accurate portrait of your humble servant), professes to wear neither gown
               nor bands, but only the very same long-eared livery in which his
               congregation is arrayed: yet, look you, one is bound to speak the truth as
               far as one knows it, whether one mounts a cap and bells or a shovel-hat; and
               a deal of disagreeable matter must come out in the course of such an
               undertaking.</p>
            <p>  I have heard a brother of the story-telling trade, at Naples, preaching to
               a pack of good-for-nothing honest lazy fellows by the sea-shore, work
               himself up into such a rage and passion with some of the villains whose
               wicked deeds he was describing and inventing, that the audience could not
               resist it; and they and the poet together would burst out into a roar of
               oaths and execrations against the fictitious monster of the tale, so that
               the hat went round, and the bajocchi tumbled into it, in the midst of a
               perfect storm of sympathy.</p>
            <p>  At the little Paris theatres, on the other hand, you will not only hear the
               people yelling out: <hi>“Ah gredin! Ah monstre!”</hi> and cursing the tyrant
               of the play from the boxes; but the actors themselves positively refuse to
               play the wicked parts, such as those of <hi>infâmes Anglais,</hi> brutal
               Cossacks, and what not, and prefer to appear at a smaller salary, in their
               real characters as loyal Frenchmen. I set the two stories one against the
               other, so that you may see that it is not from mere mercenary motives that
               the present performer is desirous to show up and trounce his villains; but
               because he has a sincere hatred of them, which he cannot not keep down, and
               which must find a vent in suitable abuse and bad language.</p>
            <p>  I warn my “kyind friends,” then, that I am going to tell a story of
               harrowing villany and complicated—but, as I trust, intensely
               interesting—crime. My rascals are not milk-and-water rascals, I promise you.
               When we come to the proper places we won’t spare fine language—No. no! But
               when we are going over the quiet country we must perforce be calm. A tempest
               in a slop-basin is absurd We will reserve that sort of thing for the mighty
               ocean and the lonely midnight. The present Chapter is very mild. Others——But
               we will not anticipate <hi>those.</hi></p>
            <p>  And, as we bring our characters forward, I will ask leave, as a man and a
               brother, not only to introduce, but occasionally to step down from the
               platform, and talk about them: if they are good and kindly, to love them and
               shake them by the hand: if they are silly, to laugh at them confidentially
               in the reader’s sleeve: if they are wicked and heartless, to abuse them in
               the strongest terms which politeness admits of.</p>
            <p>  Otherwise you might fancy it was I who was sneering at the practice of
               devotion, which Miss Sharp finds so ridiculous; that it was I who laughed
               good-humouredly at the reeling old Silenus of a baronet—whereas the laughter
               comes from one who has no reverence except for prosperity, and no eye for
               anything beyond success. Such people there are living and flourishing in the
               world—Faithless, Hopeless, Charityless: let us have at them, dear friends,
               with might and main. Some there are, and very successful too, mere quacks
               and fools: and it was to combat and expose such as those, no doubt, that
               Laughter was made.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
