<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Vanity Fair: A Novel without a Hero: ELTeC edition</title>
           <author ref="https://viaf.org/viaf/95208604/">Thackeray, William Makepeace (1811-1863)</author>
        </titleStmt>
        <extent>
           <measure unit="words">298740</measure>
        </extent>
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher ref="https://distant-reading.net">COST Action "Distant Reading for European Literary History" (CA16204)</publisher>
           <distributor ref="https://zenodo.org/communities/eltec/">Zenodo.org</distributor><date when="2020-11-14"/>
           <availability><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/></availability>
           <ref type="doi" target="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.3462435">ELTeC</ref>
           <ref type="doi" target="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4271467">ELTeC release 1.0.0</ref>
           <ref type="doi" target="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.3533868">ELTeC-eng</ref>
           <ref type="doi" target="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4271630">ELTeC-eng release 1.0.0</ref>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc><bibl type="digitalSource"><author>Thackeray, William Makepeace</author>
           <title>Vanity Fair, A Novel without a Hero. Vols. V &amp; VI</title>
           <title level="s">Harvard Classics Shelf of Fiction.</title>
           <publisher>New York: P.F. Collier &amp; Son, 1917</publisher>
           <publisher>Bartleby.com, 2000.</publisher>
           <ref target="http://www.bartleby.com/305/">Bartleby</ref></bibl>
           <bibl type="firstEdition" n="B7155">
              <author>W. M. Thackeray</author>
              <title>Vanity Fair: A Novel without a Hero</title>
              <publisher>London: Bradbury and Evans</publisher>
              <date>1848</date>
              <ref target="http://dbooks.bodleian.ox.ac.uk/books/PDFs/590972833.pdf"/>
           </bibl></sourceDesc>
     </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="chapter">
            <head>V. Dobbin of Ours</head>
            <p>CUFF’S fight with Dobbin, and the unexpected issue of that contest, will long
               be remembered by every man who was educated at Dr. Swishtail’s famous
               school. The latter youth (who used to be called Heigh-ho Dobbin, Gee-ho
               Dobbin, and by many other names indicative of puerile contempt) was the
               quietest, the clumsiest, and, as it seemed, the dullest of all Dr.
               Swishtail’s young gentlemen. His parent was a grocer in the city: and it was
               bruited abroad that he was admitted into Dr. Swishtail’s academy upon what
               are called ‘mutual principles”—that is to say, the expenses of his board and
               schooling were defrayed by his father in goods, not money; and he stood
               there—almost at the bottom of the school—in his scraggy corduroys and
               jacket, through the seams of which his great big bones were bursting—as the
               representative of so many pounds of tea, candles, sugar, mottled-soap, plums
               (of which a very mild proportion was supplied for the puddings of the
               establishment), and other commodities. A dreadful day it was for young
               Dobbin when one of the youngsters of the school, having run into the town
               upon a poaching excursion for hardbake and polonies, espied the cart of
               Dobbin &amp; Rudge, Grocers and Oilmen, Thames Street, London, at the
               Doctor’s door, discharging a cargo of the wares in which the firm dealt.</p>
            <p>  Young Dobbin had no peace after that. The jokes were frightful, and
               merciless against him. “Hullo, Dobbin,” one wag would say, “here’s good news
               in the paper. Sugars is ris’, my boy.” Another would set a sum—“If a pound
               of mutton-candles cost sevenpence-halfpenny, how much must Dobbin cost?” and
               a roar would follow from all the circle of young knaves, usher and all, who
               rightly considered that the selling of goods by retail is a shameful and
               infamous practice, meriting the contempt and scorn of all real
               gentlemen.</p>
            <p>  “Your father’s only a merchant, Osborne,” Dobbin said in private to the
               little boy who had brought down the storm upon him. At which the latter
               replied haughtily, “My father’s a gentleman, and keeps his carriage;” and
               Mr. William Dobbin retreated to a remote outhouse in the playground, where
               he passed a half-holiday in the bitterest sadness and woe. Who amongst us is
               there that does not recollect similar hours of bitter, bitter childish
               grief? Who feels injustice; who shrinks before a slight; who has a sense of
               wrong so acute, and so glowing a gratitude for kindness, as a generous boy?
               and how many of those gentle souls do you degrade, estrange, torture, for
               the sake of a little loose arithmetic, and miserable dog-latin?</p>
            <p>  Now, William Dobbin, from an incapacity to acquire the rudiments of the
               above language, as they are propounded in that wonderful book the Eton Latin
               Grammar, was compelled to remain among the very last of Doctor Swishtail’s
               scholars, and was “taken down” continually by little fellows with pink faces
               and pinafores when he marched up with the lower form, a giant amongst them,
               with his downcast, stupefied look, his dog’s-eared primer, and his tight
               corduroys. High and low, all made fun of him. They sewed up those corduroys,
               tight as they were. They cut his bed-strings. They upset buckets and
               benches, so that he might break his shins over them, which he never failed
               to do. They sent him parcels, which, when opened, were found to contain the
               paternal soap and candles. There was no little fellow but had his jeer and
               joke at Dobbin; and he bore everything quite patiently, and was entirely
               dumb and miserable.</p>
            <p>  Cuff, on the contrary, was the great chief and dandy of the Swishtail
               Seminary. He smuggled wine in. He fought the town-boys. Ponies used to come
               for him to ride home on Saturdays. He had his top-boots in his room, in
               which he used to hunt in the holidays. He had a gold repeater: and took
               snuff like the doctor. He had been to the Opera, and knew the merits of the
               principal actors, preferring Mr. Kean to Mr. Kemble. He could knock you off
               forty Latin verses in an hour. He could make French poetry. What else didn’t
               he know, or couldn’t he do? They said even the Doctor himself was afraid of
               him.</p>
            <p>  Cuff, the unquestioned king of the school, ruled over his subjects, and
               bullied them, with splendid superiority. This one blacked his shoes: that
               toasted his bread, others would fag out, and give him balls at cricket
               during whole summer afternoons. “Figs” was the fellow whom he despised most,
               and with whom, though always abusing him, and sneering at him, he scarcely
               ever condescended to hold personal communication.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
